Guide to the Caesar R. Bannihr Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Caesar R. Bannihr papers
1883-1942
MS 830
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(5 boxes)
The papers are made up almost entirely of diaries and account books that record Bannihr's business career, both as the owner of a trimming business in New York, and as an engraver and die sinker. Bannihr's early diaries (1883-1891) describe his life as a young working man in Cheshire, Connecticut, where he was active in Democratic politics and the district school committee. Included in the diaries are descriptions of his mechanical inventions. His wife also kept a diary for a portion of this period (1890-1893), which takes in the years of their courtship and early married life. Samples of Bannihr's work in the form of plaster casts, master molds, and metal dies are also in the collection.
Bannihr, Caesar R., 1857-1943
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from M. Earle, 1944.
Scope and Contents
Caesar R. Bannihr (1857-1943) was a tinkerer and an inventor, and by profession, an engraver and die sinker. All that we know about Bannihr is what can be found in the diaries and account books that are in the Bannihr Papers. Bannihr was twenty-six-years-old when he started recording the events of his daily life in the series of diaries found in these papers. From 1883-1891 Bannihr worked a ten-hour day at the Cheshire (Connecticut) Manufacturing Company. In his leisure time he invented a match box machine, a safety brake, and other gadgets; practiced drawing, piano, and guitar; bicycled and served as sales agent for the Columbia Bicycle Company; sold cigars as a small business venture with his father; attended the local Democratic Party caucuses; and served on the Committee of School District No. 12, Cheshire. It was while Bannihr was on the school committee that he started to court his future wife, Cynthia Tucker (1858-?), a teacher at the school. Since Cynthia Tucker Bannihr also kept a diary for the period 1890-1893, we can see this developing relationship from both sides. There is no diary of Caesar Bannihr's after he left Cheshire for New York in December 1891, but Cynthia Tucker Bannihr's diary shows us the plans for the October 1892 wedding and their first year of married life in New York City.
When Bannihr moved to New York, he presumably went into partnership with his brother Henry in the trimming business. There are two account books for his enterprise. However, Bannihr soon was working at the trade of engraving and die sinking. The account books from 1894-1942 would indicate that he was self-employed, but he also might have practiced his trade while holding a full-time job. The account books show not only the economic course of the business, but also the craftsmanship of Bannihr; they contain numerous sketches and samples of the dies and engravings.
The papers contain another series of diaries kept by Bannihr from 1934-1941 while he and his wife were living in Stratford, Connecticut. In these Bannihr recorded day-to-day happenings, the produce of his garden, and the decreasing work load of his later years.
The papers are arranged as follows:
Diaries of Caesar R. Bannihr,* 1883-1891; 1934-1941
Diaries of Cynthia T. Bannihr, 1890-1893
Account Books,* 1891-1942
Photograph, n.d.
Misc. printed material & sample dies 1885-1890, n. d.
*In several places Bannihr used old account books for his diary or recorded financial matters at the end of a diary volume. Where such overlap occurs has been noted in the folder list.
The papers were purchased from M. Earle, April 17, 1944.
Business; Education; Engraving (Metal-work); Working class; Science; Cheshire (Conn.); Connecticut; Account books; Diaries; Businessmen; Engravers; Labor movement; Labor; Bannihr, Caesar R., 1857-1943; Bannihr, Cynthia Tucker, b. 1858
- Inventory
  - Diaries
    - Caesar R. Bannihr
      - 1883 Sep (kept during his vacation to Boston and Maine) (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 1884 January-December (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 1885 January - December (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 1886 Jan - Dec (2 vol.); 1886 Aug 30 - Sep 6 (kept during a trip to Philadelphia) (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - 1887 Jan - Dec (2 vol.) (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 1888 Jan - Dec (2 vol.); 1888 Jun - 1889 May (Vol. contains a record of School District No. 12, Cheshire, Conn. business.) (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 1889 Jan - Dec (2 vol.); 1889 Jun - 1891 Mar (Vol. includes a record of School District No. 12, Cheshire, Conn. business with the school expense account.) (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 1890 January - December; 1891 January - December (2 vol.) (Vol. includes accounts of Bannihr as an agent for Columbia Bicycles.) (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 1934 January - 1935 January; 1935 January - August (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 1935 September - December (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 1936 Jan - Dec (Vol. includes the pages of Bannihr's account book from 1903-1905.) (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 1936 November - 1938 January (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - 1938 Jan - Feb; 1938 Feb - Sep (Vol. includes pages from a "Time Book Weekly" Account, 1896 Mar-Apr.) (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - 1938 September - 1939 June; 1939 June - 1940 April (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - 1940 May - Nov (Vol. contains a few pages of financial accounts, 1883-1884; 1894-1895.) (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - 1940 Dec - 1941 Feb (Vol. includes a few pages of salemen's commission accounts, 1893 Jan-Oct, presumably for Bannihr Bros. Trimmers.) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Cynthia Tucker Bannihr
      - 1890 January - December 1893 (Box 3, Folder 17-20)
  - Account Books:
    - Bannihr Bros. Trimmers: Accounts of Jacob H. Guggenheimer, salesman, (Vol. also includes accounts for C. R. Bannihr's die works, 1904 Aug - 1906 Sep.), 1891 October-1893 April (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Accounts of M. J. Loeb, salesman, 1894 June-September (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Caesar R.Bannihr:
      - Die works, 1894 January-1895 June (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Engraving and die works, 1895 June-1898 November (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
      - Engraver and die sinker, 1903-1905; also 1930 March-December (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Engraver and die sinker, 1906-1930 January; 1931 January-1942 March (Box 4, Folder 27-30)
  - Photograph: Caesar R. Bannihr with bicycle, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Printed material relating to Columbia Bicycles and to the League of American Wheelmen, 1885-1890 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Notes and drawings, 1936, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Die samples (Box 5, Folder 34-35)